PROFESSOR: So where are we so far?
Last lecture we defined
a search problem.
A search problem is defined by the
states in the search abstraction.
These are the configurations
of the world as relevant
to your search problem.
There are actions, which
come along with costs.
And there's a successor function which
says how the states evolve in response
your action.
In essence, the successor function
is your knowledge about
how the world works.
If I do this, what will
happen in my model?
In addition, for a search problem,
there's a start state and a goal test.
We then talked about a search tree,
which is this mathematical object
where at the top is your start state and
the nodes in this tree correspond
to all the possible plans
you could execute.
And as you get deeper into the tree this
corresponds to plans with more
and more steps.
Plans have costs, which are the sum of
the action costs that lead into them.
And what we want to do with a search
algorithm is systematically build this
search tree starting at the top,
building towards a goal, and we'd like
to do this in a way that one, doesn't
expand too much of the tree because
these trees are huge.
Actually, in general, a lot of the
things we care about in AI, in
principle, are exponential in the worst
case and we want, in practice,
do as little work as possible.
And these search algorithms primarily
differed in their ordering of the
fringe, so how we decided which
partial plan to expand next.
In addition, we started at the end of
last class talking about optimality,
which is this notion of not just finding
a way of achieving my goal,
but doing it in the lowest cost where
the costs are encoded in the successor
functions costs.
PROFESSOR: So here's an example
of a search that has
nothing to do with pathing.
Lots of people like to latch onto this
idea that search is moving from one
place in a maze to an exit.
Lots of search problems look nothing
like positional planning.
So in the pancake problem, you have a
stack of pancakes and you would like
to get them in order where the biggest
pancake is on the bottom, and the
smallest pancake is on top.
But the only way you can do this as
you're cooking the pancakes is to
insert your spatula at some point
in the stack and do a flip.
So if I insert here and I do a flip,
the top two will switch positions.
If I flip below that, I'll actually
get to the goal state here.
And if I flip even further, I'll
just flip the entire stack.
So at any given point, my state is
some ordering of the pancakes.
My actions are the places
I can insert my spatula.
And the successor function does the
appropriate flipping of the prefixes
of these orders.
OK, that's a search problem.
It's perfectly well defined, and
it has nothing to do with x, y
coordinates or positions.
So if we wanted to have a cost for
this, one thing we could do is we
could just say minimize
the number of flips.
Then the cost would all be one.
But it takes more energy to flip more
pancakes, and so maybe we could say
the cost is the number
of pancakes flipped.
Who cares about this kind of
pancake flipping problem?
You might think this is only for some
pancake flipping robot, but you'd be
surprised who has thought
about this problem.
In fact, probably the last two people
you'd ever think of, and particularly
the last two people you'd ever think
would be working together on the
pancake problem, which is Bill Gates
and Christos Papadimitriou.
They like pancakes.
OK, so what does this look like
as a state space search graph?
Well, it looks something like this.
Remember, the nodes of this
configuration of the world, which in
this case are just pancake orderings,
in this case the arcs are
bi-directional and they have a cost.
That cost depends on how many
pancakes I flipped.
And here is a way to graph that
encodes the search problem.
Now again, this fits on the slide.
For a big problem, this wouldn't
fit on the slide.
And we somehow need to be able to find
our goal in this kind of a graph
without building the entire graph.
All right, so in particular for this
graph, here is your goal state, and
you start somewhere.
Who knows where you start.
Maybe you start here.
And you have to find some way of getting
through this graph of least
cost that gets to your goal.
PROFESSOR: How did we do this?
We have this general algorithm that
we're going to continue using today,
and we're going to improve
it in two ways.
The general algorithm involved the key
idea of a search tree and a fringe.
At the beginning, you start with the
start state, which is the empty plan
where you've done nothing and you're
just sitting at the start.
That's the root of the tree, and it is
the initial thing on your fringe.
As you execute this algorithm, it's
a very simple, short cycle.
You take something off the fringe, you
put its children from the successor
function on the fringe, and those
actions that generated the children
have costs as well as result states.
You stick all of that onto the fringe,
and then you continue going.
You take something off the fringe and
put its children on, you take
something else off the fringe and put
its children on, and this frontier,
the fringe, moves more or less
downward in the tree.
And whether it goes uniformly downward
or mostly on the left, that's going to
be the difference between the algorithms
like depth-first search and
breadth-first search.
As we go, we add up the costs.
Some search algorithms are sensitive to
that cumulative cost, some of them
aren't, but each plan has a cost.
Here, this plan has cost 7.
It happens to be the optimal cost.
And this particular plan
achieves the goal.
We keep taking things off the fringe
and putting their children on until
something removed from the fringe
satisfies the goal, at which
point, we return it.
Super critical.
You return the first plan removed from
the fringe that achieves your goal,
not the first plan put into
the fringe, and we'll see
today why that's important.
All right, so we saw depth-first search,
we saw breadth-first search,
we saw uniform-cost search.
We're going to see two more today.
And I talked about them as if they're
all basically the same thing except
for how you decide what
comes off the fringe.
What does that mean in terms
of implementation?
Well, in terms of implementation, it
actually means that you can literally
implement one search algorithm, feel
free to do this in your project ones,
you can implement one time and
simply pass in variable
strategies in some way.
Conceptually, all the fringes we've
talked about are priority queues.
There's a bunch of plans that are yet
to be expanded on on the fringe, and
each one has some number that
represents its priority.
In breadth-first, the priority is take
off from the fringe the thing that has
the shallowest, the shortest, plan so
far in terms of number of steps.
Uniform cost was the cheapest
in terms of total path cost.
Depth-first was the deepest, so the
opposite of breadth-first search.
Now, in practice for depth-first search
and breadth-first search, you
don't actually need a priority
queue to get their behaviors.
So if you want a depth-first search,
you basically want to expand next
whatever you put on most recently,
because it's the deepest.
And so you can just use a stack and
take whatever's off the stack.
That means you don't need to have the
overhead for a priority queue.
A general priority queue, putting things
on and taking things off incurs
a login penalty.
So in general, with a priority queue, if
you have a certain number of knows
that you're putting on the queue and
taking off of the queue, then you're
going to get a log that many factor to
represent the fact that really the
queue is capable of sorting.
You put everything on, you
take everything off, now
they're in sorted order.
You don't want to pay that if you don't
have to, so you'll see that
depth-first search and breadth-first
search are usually implemented using
stacks and queues, but in principle,
it's all just priority queues.
That is the one queue, it solves
all search problems,
sometimes you can optimize.
All right.
So last time we finished
out uninformed search.
In uninformed search, we explore this
tree in some sense from the top down.
Depth-first search is more like
from the left to the right.
We explore this tree in some
way that is systematic.
Left to right or top down,
or cheapest things first.
Systematic but unaware of
where the goals are.
So even if the goal is down and to the
right, breadth-first search will still
do the first layer then the second
than the third layer.
It doesn't know where it's going.
It just does its thing.
PROFESSOR: Particularly in uniform
cost search, the strategy was to
expand the lowest path cost, and we'd
convinced ourselves that uniform cost
search is both complete and optimal
under certain conditions.
And so the reason why it works is
because you start at the top and you
basically work your way
systematically down.
And when you find a goal, you find the
cheapest goal in terms of cost.
And when you do that, you've
expanded all plans that are
that cheap or cheaper.
So the good is uniform cost search
is complete and optimal.
The bad was it kind of explored
outward in every direction.
And let's see that in a
couple different ways.
So one way I can show you that
happening is to look
at this search demo.
Here is just a bunch of open water,
green is the start state, red is the
stop state.
If I execute a uniform cost search, the
dots will show the order in which
states are first expanded.
And you can see it just
radiates outward.
It's checking all of the things that
it can do in say, seven steps until
finally, it finds a plan
that hits the goal.
Which means, in addition to going right,
it's also going left, which
isn't very useful.
Let's see this in a different way.
OK here is in a Pac-Man configuration
here, red indicates something expanded
earlier, and closer to black indicates
something that was expanded later.
Black is the things that
weren't expanded all.
You can see we considered all the
states nearby the Pac-Man.
And basically, we had to consider the
entire board because in the cost it
takes you to get to the goal, the dot
in the lower left, you can basically
get anywhere and so you expand
the whole board.
It's optimal, but you kind of did almost
everything you could possibly
do in terms of work.
So we'd like to improve on that.